Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is י"ד, Yud Daled,
סנהדרין Sanhedrin 14. We pick up with on י"ג עמוד ב, Yud
Gimmel Amud Bais, like four lines from the bottom. And we've just
started discussing the idea, you know, the משנה Mishnah said that you
require three for סמיכת זקנים, Semikhat Zekeinim, which is the classic סמיכה
Semikhah that the real סמיכה Semikhah going all the way back to
משה רבנו, Moshe Rabbeinu, the authority to represent God, to be called
a בית דין Beis Din of אלהים Elohim and to be דייני
קנסות Dinei Kenasot to exert power
to give מלקות, Malkos, administer מלקות Malkos and מיתת
בית דין Misos Beis Din and do all the types of things
that are require that are real punishments of the court and that
embody that sense of divine authority. So now the גמרא Gemara so
that said that you needed three. All right, and now the גמרא
Gemara is saying questions this. So four lines from the bottom,
so the גמרא Gemara says וחד לא סמיך? v'chad lo samikh? Is
this really true that we can't have one person to give סמיכה?
Semikhah? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, but
didn't רב יהודה Rav Yehuda say in the name of רב, Rav,
ברם זכור אותו איש לטוב, Baram zakhor oso ish letov, this that
this man should be remembered for good, ורבי יהודה בן בבא שמו.
v'Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava shemo. Not just a man, it's a רבי
יהודה בן בבא. Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava. שאלמלא
הוא נשתכחו דיני קנסות מישראל. She-ilmalei hu nishtakhu dinei kenasos mi-Yisrael. If
it were not for what he had done, the laws of קנס
kenas would have been forgotten amongst the Jewish people. So the גמרא
Gemara says נשתכחו ניגרסינהו? Nishtakhu nigresinhu? What do you mean they would
have been forgotten? Let's just learn them. I mean you don't need
because this man didn't do anything that made us retain that knowledge.
אלא, Ella, rather, no, we don't mean that. We mean, top of
י"ד עמוד א, Yud Daled Amud Aleph, בטלו דיני קנסות מישראל, Batlu
dinei kenasos mi-Yisrael, that we never we would have lost the authority
to actually rule in דיני קנסות dinei kenasos and מלקות malkos and
מיתת בית דין misos beis din and the whole סמיכה Semikhah would
have been broken, would have been lost if it had not been
for him. Why is that? Why would the chain have been broken?
שפעם אחת גזרה מלכות הרשעה גזרה על ישראל. She-pa'am achat gazra malkhus
harisha gezeira al Yisrael. Once the wicked government Rome made an edict
against the Jewish people, this is in the time of like the
Hadrianic persecutions, we'll see this is right around the time of רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva students, כל הסומך יהרג,
kol ha-somekh yeihareg, anybody who gives סמיכה, Semikhah, who gives this passing
on of this Rabbinic divine authority will be killed, וכל הנסמך יהרג,
v'khol ha-nismakh yeihareg, anybody
who receives סמיכה Semikhah will be killed, ועיר שסומכין בה תחרב, v'ir
she-somkhin bah tekharev, and the city that this takes place in will
be laid waste,
ותחומים שסמוכין להן יעקרו, u-sekhumim she-semukhim lahen ye'akru, and anything that was
within the city limits of those cities would also be uprooted. מה
עשה יהודה בן בבא? Ma asa Yehuda ben Bava?
So what did יהודה בן בבא Yehuda ben Bava do? Because apparently
you know there was somehow threatened now what happened to everybody who
had סמיכה Semikhah at that time, so maybe they were all being
persecuted and killed by the Romans, or maybe it doesn't matter, they
would have died out, nobody was the next generation wasn't receiving it.
So what did he do? הלך וישב לו בין שני הרים גדולים,
Halakh v'yashav lo bein shnei harim gedolim, he situated himself between two
big mountains, ובין שתי עיירות גדולות, u-vein shtei ayaros gedolos, between two
large cities, ובין שני תחומי שבת, u-vein shnei techumei Shabbos, and between
two of the תחומי techumim of the boundaries of the city or
you know the areas outside of the cities, בין אושא לשפרעם, bein
Usha l'Shefaram, between these two cities אושא Usha which we know אושא
Usha was a major place of the בית דין Beis Din and
שפרעם. Shefaram. And so he was out there in a place where
he wasn't in a city so there was no city that could
have been destroyed and if it they would have had to do
it they would have had to destroy two major cities so it
wouldn't have been feasible. So he did it in a way that
hopefully would have protected everybody other than of course himself and the
people receiving the סמיכה. Semikhah. So what did he do though? וסמך
שם חמשה זקנים, V'samakh sham chamisha zekeinim, and he gave סמיכה Semikhah
to five elders. ואלו הן, V'eilu hen, רבי מאיר ורבי יהודה ורבי
שמעון ורבי יוסי ורבי אלעזר בן שמוע. Rabbi Meir v'Rabbi Yehuda v'Rabbi
Shimon v'Rabbi Yosi v'Rabbi Elazar ben Shammua. So these are like classic
you know the generation towards the end of the תנאים, Tannaim, the
תלמידי רבי עקיבא, talmidei Rabbi Akiva, and we'll see in a minute
where's רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva sort of factoring in here if he's
the previous generation. But anyway he gave them all סמיכה. Semikhah. רב
אבא מוסיף אף רבי נחמיה. Rav Abba mosif af Rabbi Nechemiah. רב
אבא Rav Abba added רבי נחמיה. Rabbi Nechemiah. כיון שהכירו אויבים בהם,
Keivan she-hikkiru oyvim bahen,
once the enemies recognized what was happening, not exactly clear why you
just can't do this all very hush-hush, why does it why is
it something that automatically becomes public, one wonders exactly what the
historical reality was sort of at this time. But anyway, כיון שהכירו
אויבים בהם, keivan she-hikkiru oyvim bahen, אמר להם
בני רוצו, amar lahen bnai rutzu, my sons run, run, you know
my sons run run, you like get away get away, I'll stand
here and I'll and I'll protect you, you run. He said to
all those who received סמיכה. Semikhah. אמרו לו רבי מה תהא עליך,
Amru lo Rabbi mah tehei alekha, what's going to happen to you?
אמר להם הריני מוטל לפניהם כאבן שאין לה הופכין, Amar lahen hareini
mutal lifneihem k'even she-ein lah hophikhin, I will stand before them like
a rock, an immovable rock. אמרו לא זזו משם, Amru lo zazu
misham, they did not move from
there, עד שננעצו בו שלש מאות לונקיות של ברזל, ad she-nitsu bo
shlosha meos lunkiyos shel barzel, until 300 you know... but anyway, it's
all very hard to understand, like, why couldn't they run after the
other students as they were running after him? How was he sort
of, what was he doing to hold down the fort to allow
them to escape? How did they find out about it? But anyway,
this is the story that he was the one that was brave
enough and risked his life and gave up his life in order
to pass down this סמיכה smicha going all the way back to
משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. ועשוהו ככברה, v'asu k'khivra,
and they made him like a sieve. רבי יהודה בן בבא, Rabbi
Yehuda ben Bava, so now anyway, that is a very powerful story
and telling us something about the chain of סמיכה, smicha, but the
question is, it sounds like he was the only one who did
it and you said you needed three people to do סמיכה. smicha.
So the גמרא Gemara says, רבי יהודה בן בבא, Rabbi Yehuda ben
Bava, אחריני הוו בהדיה, achrini hava bahadei, no, there was two other
people with him, others there. והאי דלא חשיב להו משום כבודו דרבי
יהודה בן בבא, v'hai d'lo khashivlu mishum kvodo d'Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava,
they didn't mention it because of his honor, he was the only
guy that really mattered, he just took two other people, I mean
the other two must have had סמיכה, smicha, but he took them
all, took them with him, but he was the one whom the
story, we wanted to tell the story about. Of course, one wonders
what happened to the other two, did they also get killed? Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara wants to wrap up this story. רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, רבי יהודה בן בבא Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava סמכיה, samchei,
is it really true that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir received סמיכה smicha
from רבי יהודה בן בבא? Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava? ואמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן כל האומר רבי מאיר לא סמכו רבי
עקיבא אינו אלא טועה, v'amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan
kol ha'omer Rabbi Meir lo samcho Rabbi Akiva eino ela to'eh, if
you say that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir did not get סמיכה smicha
from רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, you're mistaken. Very funny statement, whoever says
he didn't get סמיכה, smicha, like was somebody saying it? Presumably somebody
was saying it, and he wanted to counter that. So you see
this really makes an emphasis that it was רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
who gave him סמיכה, smicha, these were all תלמידי רבי עקיבא. talmidei
Rabbi Akiva. So the גמרא Gemara says, so no, סמכיה רבי עקיבא
ולא קבלוהו, samchei Rabbi Akiva v'lo kiblo, they, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
gave him סמיכה, smicha, but he wasn't accepted yet as an authority
by the community. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, third line from
the top, לפי שעדיין היה בחור, l'fi she'adayin haya bachur, maybe רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva thought that he had the learning, but maybe he
had the learning, he didn't have the wisdom, he didn't have the
gravitas, the community was not yet ready to accept him. ולא סמכו.
v'lo samcho. סמכיה רבי יהודה בן בבא וקבלוהו, samchei Rabbi Yehuda ben
Bava v'kiblo, and
but after רבי יהודה בן בבא Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava gave him
סמיכה, smicha, then they did accept it, presumably because רבי יהודה בן
בבא's Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava סמיכה smicha was greater than רבי עקיבא's,
Rabbi Akiva but at that time he was, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
was of a stage that people were prepared to recognize the סמיכה.
smicha. And maybe this is a little bit why it became public,
how who know, like how did it become public the minute he
was giving them סמיכה? smicha? The גמרא Gemara might have simplified the
story, but obviously if somebody raise, is raised to an authority and
then is seen as an authority by the community, that is something
that the government might figure out has happened.
Okay.
Now, גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי אין
סמיכה בחוצה לארץ, amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi ein smicha b'chutz la'aretz,
you don't have סמיכה smicha outside of Israel, which is interesting, I
mean a lot of these things are just being like asserted about
this whole idea of סמיכה, smicha, like how do you know three?
The גמרא Gemara said it should be either one or seventy-one, now
it's also only in חוצה לארץ. chutz la'aretz. Of course, the original
סמיכה smicha wasn't only in חוצה לארץ, chutz la'aretz, it was משה
Moshe gave it to
יהושע, Yehoshua, but similarly to an idea that fundamentally נבואה nevuah is
only in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, so fundamentally this authority that is, it's derived
from משה, Moshe, but it's ultimately as a representing God, that is
something that the source of that has to be coming from Israel.
Okay. So אין סמיכה, ein smicha, where were we? Okay. אין סמיכה
בחוצה לארץ. ein smicha b'chutz la'aretz.
Now, מאי אין סמיכה? mai ein smicha? What does that mean? אילימא
דלא דייני דיני קנסות כלל בחוצה לארץ, ilei d'lo daini dinei k'nasos
klal b'chutz la'aretz, if it means that the סמיכה smicha is not
operative in חוצה לארץ, chutz la'aretz, even where, even if you received
סמיכה smicha in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you don't have that authority
when you're in חוצה לארץ, chutz la'aretz, that's not true.
והתנן, v'ha tnan, we talked in a משנה Mishna in מכות, Makkos,
סנהדרין נוהגת בין בארץ בין בחוצה לארץ, Sanhedrin noheget bein ba'aretz bein
b'chutz la'aretz, that the סנהדרין Sanhedrin can operate in חוצה לארץ. chutz
la'aretz. And we have an idea of שליחותייהו עבדינן, shlikhuta'ihu kavidnan, even
if we don't have סמיכה, smicha, we can see ourselves as representing
some prior בית דין Beis Din that did have סמיכה, smicha, but
here this משנה Mishna is saying fundamentally the סנהדרין Sanhedrin can operate
in חוצה לארץ. chutz la'aretz. Okay, which means that your סמיכה smicha
is operative in חוצה לארץ. chutz la'aretz. אלא, ella, fine, it doesn't
mean that, we probably would have thought it meant that, but what
it means is, אלא דלא סמכינן בחוצה לארץ, ella d'lo samkhinan b'chutz
la'aretz, that we actually don't give the סמיכה smicha in חוצה לארץ,
chutz la'aretz, that passing on of authority has to happen in ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. פשיטא, peshita, so now the גמרא Gemara says that's
obvious, I'm sorry, excuse me, פשיטא סומכין בחוצה לארץ ונסמכין בארץ, peshita
somkhin b'chutz la'aretz v'nismakhin ba'aretz,
it's obvious if the people giving סמיכה smicha were outside of Israel
and those receiving it were in Israel, אמרינן דלא, hamrinan d'lo, that's
clear that you're excluding that, meaning it's clear that the point is
that the authority to grant it, to be representing the source of
authority, you have to be situated in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the
one granting it. So that's clear that if the סומכין somkhin are
חוצה לארץ chutz la'aretz it doesn't matter even if the נסמכין, nismakhin,
the ones receiving it, are in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. פשיטא, peshita,
okay, that's obvious, אמרינן דלא. hamrinan d'lo. אלא ella what we want
to know is the flip, סומכין בארץ ונסמכין בחוצה לארץ מאי? somkhin
ba'aretz v'nismakhin b'chutz la'aretz mai? Let's say the ones giving
And the ones receiving it are in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, okay,
you know, maybe you know that you don't have to, the גמרא
Gemara before said, you know, you don't have to, סמכינן ליה בשמיה,
samchinan lei bishmei, you don't have to put your hand on it,
on the person receiving it, you just call him רבי, Rebbe, you
know, maybe you do that by sending a letter or we can
make actually an absurd case or what absurd, whatever, imagine two people
are standing on different sides of the border of ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael and חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. Okay, if you want to have
an imagine a case where they're actually able to see one another.
But before we said you don't even have to, you know, it's
סמכינן ליה בשמיה, samchinan lei bishmei, you don't have to do it
with your hands. So can that work since the source of the
authority is ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, can the recipients be in חוץ
לארץ? chutz la'aretz? Now you can frame this in two ways. Number
one is to receive that authority and then be vested in it.
You also have to be anchored in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or
at least physically present and therefore it's an ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
question, which is what it sounds like. Or the question could be
is can you give סמיכה smicha at a distance? And the גמרא
Gemara is going to seem to answer the second question, that the
problem is being at a distance, not really about being in חוץ
לארץ. chutz la'aretz. Let's take a look. תא שמע, Ta shema, come
in here. רבי יוחנן הוי מצטער אלוה דרב שמן בר אבא דלא
הוה גביה דליסמכיה. Rabbi Yochanan hava mitzta'er alei deRav Shemen bar Abba
d'lo hava gabei d'lismachiei. Rabbi Yochanan was anguished over רב שמן בר
אבא, Rav Shemen bar Abba, you know, was not by him, you
know, was not present
near him, that he never, they were never able to get together
that he could give him סמיכה. smicha. So why didn't he just
give him סמיכה smicha at a distance? So the fact that he
really wanted to and he was anguished that he couldn't because they
were never in the same place at the same time shows that
you have to be physically present in the same place and that's
why this ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz thing doesn't
work, not so much the חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, but that you
need to be in the same place. רבי שמעון בן זירוד וחד
דעמיה, Rabbi Shimon ben Zirod v'chad d'imei, and now we're going to
see similar stories about this.
רבי שמעון בן זירוד וחד דעמיה, Rabbi Shimon ben Zirod v'chad d'imei,
and now
ומנו רבי יונתן בן עכמאי, u'manu Rabbi Yonatan ben Achmai, and that
was רבי יונתן בן עכמאי. Rabbi Yonatan ben Achmai. ואמרי
לה, v'amrei lah, some say no, this story was told the other
way. רבי יונתן בן עכמאי וחד דעמיה ומנו רבי שמעון בן זירוד.
Rabbi Yonatan ben Achmai v'chad d'imei u'manu Rabbi Shimon ben Zirod. That
was רבי יונתן בן עכמאי Rabbi Yonatan ben Achmai plus another guy
who was it, it was רבי שמעון בן זירוד. Rabbi Shimon ben
Zirod. So everybody agrees it was these two, but the question sort
of is how was the story told and who was the focus
and who was like the add-on.
Anyway,
חד דהוה גביה סמכוהו, chad d'hava gabei samchuhi, the one of those
two that was by him, presumably רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, he was
able to give him סמיכה. smicha. וחד דלא הוה גביה לא סמכוהו,
v'chad d'lo hava gabei lo samchuhi, and the one that wasn't by
him, he didn't give him סמיכה. smicha. So again another evidence that
you need to be present in order to receive
סמיכה. smicha. The מסמיך masmich and the נסמך nismach have to be
in the same place. Now I actually
might have been mistaken when I said that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
was the one that they were referring to even though רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan was the one referred back. I'm realizing now that it
says סמכוהו samchuhi in the plural.
So actually it just means the generic whoever it was who was
giving סמיכה smicha gave סמיכה smicha to one of them who was
present and wasn't able to give סמיכה smicha to the other who
wasn't present. So we have one story about רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
who wasn't able to because the נסמך nismach wasn't present, one story
about some generic חכמים Chachamim who weren't, who were only able to
do it to the one who was present, not the one who
wasn't present. And again we are seeing that you need to be
present, but again not an issue of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. Okay, continuing on. רבי חנינא ורבי הושעיה הוו
קמשתדלי רבי יוחנן למיסמכינהו. Rabbi Chanina v'Rabbi Oshaya havu kamishtadlei Rabbi Yochanan
lemismachinhu. Now we're back to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So רבי חנינא
Rabbi Chanina and רבי הושעיה, Rabbi Oshaya, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was
like, you
know, working on trying to give them סמיכה, smicha, you know, really
sort of applying himself to try to give them סמיכה. smicha. ולא
הוה מסתייעא מילתא. v'lo hava mistaya milta. But it didn't work out.
Again I don't know what it means it didn't work out. It
didn't work out
that they could be together in the same place? It didn't work
out because what's really not clear here, here was was alluded to
in the גמרא Gemara before, which is about קיבלו kiblu and לא
קיבלו, lo kiblu, like whether the ציבור tzibur would have had the
buy-in and ready to accept the person. If that was that the
issue, you know, how much did this sort of require recognition of
the ציבור? tzibur? So it's a little like you really wonder what
else were the context and the realities that were required here and
why was it so difficult. But okay, ולא הוה מסתייעא מילתא. v'lo
hava mistaya milta. So was not, things weren't coming together to make
it happen. הוה קא מצטער. hava ka mitzta'er. He was very anguished.
אמרו לו. amru lo. So they said to him, "אם לא נצטער
מר," im lo nitzta'er mar, you know, don't be מצטער, mitzta'er, meaning
they, the נסמכין, nismachin, the ones he wanted to give it to.
So they said to him, now if they said, were
they there in the same place? So then the issue of geography
wasn't a problem. Maybe they sent him a letter. But it sounds
like other factors that were relevant. Anyway, they said to him, don't
be
anguished, "דאנן מדבית עלי קאתינן." d'anan m'devei Eli katinan. We're descendants of
the house of עלי, Eli, you know, עלי הכהן. Eli HaKohen. דאמר
רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן מנין שאין נסמכין לבית עלי.
d'amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan minayin she'ein nismachin l'vei
Eli. You know, we know that there's a tradition that those that
descendants of the house of עלי Eli are never able to will
never succeed in actual... receiving סמיכה, smicha, getting that authority, שנאמר ולא
יהיה זקן בביתך כל הימים. shene'emar velo yihyeh zaken be'veitcha kol hayamim.
There will not be an elder in your house all the days.
So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי זקן? mai zaken? What does that
mean, that curse to the house of Eli?
אילימא זקן ממש, eilima zaken mamash, literally you nobody who descends from
you will grow old in age, והכתיב וכל מרבית ביתך ימותו אנשים,
vehaktiv vechol marbit beitcha yamutu anashim, it already says, you know, that
the people of your house will die when they are still, you
know, young men. So, therefore obviously nobody is going to grow into
an old man. Now you might just say it's being repeated for
emphasis, but the גמרא Gemara says no, it's coming to tell you
another curse. אלא סמיכה, ela smicha, it means nobody will be, besides
that they won't live to an old age, nobody will be a
זקן, zaken, an elder, you know, a חכם, chacham, somebody with that
authority as an elder, nobody will receive סמיכה. smicha.
Okay. So,
רבי זירא הוה מיטמר למיסמכיה. Rabbi Zeira hava mitmar lemismichei.
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira was hiding because he didn't want to be
to receive סמיכה. smicha. Again, this gets to the idea of you
have to be geographically present. דאמר רבי אלעזר, de'amar Rabbi Elazar, so
he didn't want סמיכה. smicha. דאמר רבי אלעזר לעולם הוי קביל וקיים.
de'amar Rabbi Elazar le'olam hevei kabil vekayam. You should you should always
strive to be, you know,
dark, literally קביל kabil means like dark, like invisible, and then you'll
live. You know, don't take positions of authority, don't put yourself out.
It's just going to be a lot of צרות. tzaros. So with
סמיכה smicha not only came דיני קנסות, dinei knasos, but as we're
seeing here that gravitas, that authority, that representing the tradition, you know,
being a rabbi in a public type of a way and with
real authority. So, so he said he didn't want that, he didn't
want that responsibility. Make yourself lowly and then you will survive. כיון
דשמעה להא דרבי אלעזר, keivan desham'ah le'ha de'Rabbi Elazar, but when he
heard this statement of רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, אין אדם עולה לגדולה
אלא אם כן מוחלין לו על כל עוונותיו, ein adam oleh ligdulah
ela im ken mochlin lo al kol avonotav, that nobody gets a
position of authority if it were not that they up in heaven
they would forgive all of his sins. So by perhaps taking that
authority, being willing to shoulder that authority, you know, up in heaven
they give you, that that is a that achieves a degree of
כפרה kaparah for your sins. מוחלין לו על כל עוונותיו. mochlin lo
al kol avonotav. So now that he heard that oh, there is
something good that comes from taking authority, אמצי ליה אנפשיה. amtzei lei
anafshei.
So he made himself available to receive סמיכה. smicha. כי סמכוהו לרבי
זירא. ki samchu'hu le'Rabbi Zeira.
Now, when they gave סמיכה smicha to רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, this
was the one that we were just talking about that was not
seeking it. שרו ליה הכי. sharu lei hachi. This is how they
would sing to him, you know, they had a whole ceremony. לא
כחל ולא שרק ולא פירכוס ויעלת חן. lo kachal velo srak velo
pirchus veya'alat chen.
You know, without, you know, without eye shadow and without rouge and
without hair gel, and the כלה kallah is still beautiful. You know,
the כלה kallah has natural beauty, she doesn't need any makeup, and
that is רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, he's such a such an ענו
anav and a and a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham that without any
adornment, you know, his inner beauty shines through.
Very beautiful. כי סמכוהו לרבי אמי ולרבי אסי. ki samchu'hu le'Rabbi Ami
u'le'Rabbi Assi. When they gave סמיכה smicha to רבי אמי Rabbi Ami
and רבי אסי, Rabbi Assi, שרו להו הכי. sharu lehu hachi. Here's
what they would sing to them: כל מן דין כל מן דין
סמוכו לנא. kol min dein kol min dein somchu lana. Anybody like
this, anyone like this, you know, give סמיכה smicha be מסימך masmich
for our sake. And by the way, who are the people singing?
Was it the collection of rabbis? No, it sounds like give סמכו
לנא somchu lana for our sake. It sounds like it was something
that was very done with public and the community, and again that
speaks to the idea of the community buy-in. Okay. So, oh my
god, anybody like this, we'd love to have more people that get
סמיכה smicha like that person. לא תסמוכו לנא לא מסרמיטין ולא מסרמיסין.
lo tismchu lana lo misarmitin velo misarmisin. Don't give סמיכה smicha for
our sake, meaning for the community's sake,
okay,
לא תסמוכו לנא לא מסרמיטין ולא מסרמיסין, lo tismchu lana lo misarmitin
velo misarmisin, and not מסרמיטין misarmitin and not מסרמיסין, misarmisin, like bad
guys. Okay. So רש"י Rashi says, what does this mean? רש"י Rashi
says, you know, one of them means a rag, like, you know,
worthless people, maybe blown-up people who are full of themselves but don't
have real תורה, Torah, or people that pervert things, like we don't
want any, you know, fake rabbis. We want somebody that really is
the real stuff. ואמרי לה לא מחמיסין ולא מטרמיסין. ve'amri lah lo
machmisin velo matremisin. And others say different types of things. Not people
that are thieves. רש"י Rashi says it means that they hold back
תורה, Torah, maybe it means that they will compromise their integrity for
money, and the מטרמיסין, matremisin, רש"י Rashi doesn't doesn't know what that
means. But clearly, don't give us bad, corrupt rabbis, or rabbis that
are just full of themselves or don't know anything, give us the
real deal. רבי אבהו כי הוי אתי ממתיבתא לבי קיסר. Rabbi Abbahu
ki hava ati mimativta le'vei Keisar. When רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu would
come from the
ישיבה yeshiva to the Caesar's house,
we've seen before, you know, the rabbis would have doings with the
Roman government, נפקי אמהתא דבי קיסר. nafki amhata de'vei Keisar. So the
matron, one of the women of the Caesar's house, would come out,
ומשרו
ליה, u'mesharu lei, and they would sing the following, because we're talking
about
רבא דעמי rabba d'amei the leader or the rabbi you know of
his people מדברנא דאומתי midbarna d'umsei the leader of his nation בוצינא
דנהורא botzina d'nehura it is actually language that gets used a lot
in the זהר zohar בוצינא דנהורא botzina d'nehura the candle of light
בריך מתייך לשלם brich maseich l'shalom blessed is your coming in peace.
One imagines that they said that in Greek or in Latin, not
in Aramaic. Okay, anyway, that is the end of the discussion of
סמיכת זקנים. smichas zekenim. Moving on now to the next topic in
the משנה, mishna, right, we're going through the משנה, mishna, so the
משנה mishna said what? The משנה mishna said, where was it? סמיכת
זקנים ועריפת עגלה בשלושה דברי רבי שמעון רבי יהודה אומר בחמישה. smichas
zekenim va'arifat egla bishlosha divrei rebbi shimon rebbi yehuda omer bachamisha.
Okay, so now there's a debate of רבי יהודה rebbi yehuda and
רבי שמעון rebbi shimon whether עגלה ערופה egla arufa is with three
or with five. תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, עריפת עגלה בשלושה. arifat egla
bishlosha. תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, ויצאו זקניך ושופטיך, veyatzu zekenecha veshoftecha, your
elders and your judges will go out. זקניך, zekenecha, שנים, shnayim, ושופטיך,
veshoftecha, שנים, shnayim, ואין בית דין שקול מוסיפין עליהם עוד אחד. v'ein
beis din shakol mosifin aleihem od echad. Okay,
so that's how you get the five, that's the position of the
five. הרי כאן חמישה דברי רבי יהודה, harei kan chamisha divrei rebbi
yehuda, that's רבי יהודה. rebbi yehuda. So in the ברייתא braita רבי
יהודה rebbi yehuda spells out where he's getting it from. רבי שמעון
אומר, rebbi shimon omer, זקניך שנים ואין בית דין שקול מוסיפין עליהם
עוד אחד הרי כאן שלושה. zekenecha shnayim v'ein beis din shakol mosifin
aleihem od echad harei kan shlosha. I only read the word זקניך,
zekenecha, two, you can't have two, so it's three, and that's how
you get three. I don't read the word שופטיך shoftecha to get
you another two. So the גמרא gemara asks the obvious question: ורבי
שמעון הא שופטיך מאי עביד ליה? v'rebbi shimon ha shoftecha mai avid
lei? What does he do with the word שופטיך? shoftecha? מיבעי ליה
מיוחדים שבשופטיך mibaei lei miyuchadim shebeshoftecha
to tell you that it is the select ones of your judges,
meaning that it comes from the בית דין הגדול, beis din hagadol,
that it's not just any בית דין. beis din. רבי יהודה? rebbi
yehuda? מזקני זקניך נפקא. miziknei zekenecha nafka. רבי יהודה rebbi yehuda gets
it from the fact that it could have said זקני ziknei and
it says זקניך, zekenecha, yours, meaning like the special ones, the select
ones. Okay. רבי שמעון, rebbi shimon, אי מזקני הוה אמינא זקני השוק
כתב רחמנא זקניך. ee miziknei hava amina ziknei hashuk kasav rachmana zekenecha.
No,
it had to write זקניך. zekenecha. זקניך zekenecha itself would not have
meant the select ones because if it had just said זקני ziknei
it would have just meant old people, I wouldn't have thought it
meant, you know, judges and the people that have
סמיכה. smicha. So זקניך zekenecha yours means select, but select not meaning
סנהדרין בית דין הגדול, sanhedrin beis din hagadol, just select as real
like judges, not סתם stam older people. So כתב רחמנא זקניך. kasav
rachmana zekenecha. ואי כתב זקניך, vee kasav zekenecha, but now but that
wouldn't have led me to say that I would have needed the
בית דין הגדול. beis din hagadol. הוה אמינא סנהדרין קטנה, hava amina
sanhedrin ktana, they could even come from the from a בית דין
beis din from the small סנהדרין sanhedrin of twenty-three. כתב רחמנא ושופטיך
מיוחדים שבשופטיך. kasav rachmana v'shoftecha miyuchadim shebeshoftecha.
Okay, that's why I needed שופטיך shoftecha still gets me the idea
of בית דין הגדול beis din hagadol and not to tell me
more דיינים. dayanim. רבי יהודה? rebbi yehuda? גמיר זקני זקני
מוכסמכו זקני העדה את ידיהם. gamir ziknei ziknei miv'samchu ziknei ha'eida es
yadeihem. So he learns a גזירה שוה gzera shava from וסמכו זקני
העדה
את ידיהם v'samchu ziknei
ha'eida es
yadeihem by the פר העלם דבר של ציבור, par helam davar shel
tzibur, when, you know, the בית דין הגדול beis din hagadol makes
an error in their הוראה. hora'ah. Okay, and that clearly is context
is the בית דין הגדול. beis din hagadol. So he makes a
גזירה שוה. gzera shava. על הלן מיוחדים שבעדה אף כאן מיוחדים שבזקניך.
al halan miyuchadim sheba'eida af kan miyuchadim shebiziknecha.
So it's also זקני העדה ziknei ha'eida the ה, hei, you know,
the special ones, that's the בית דין הגדול, beis din hagadol, and
therefore if that's what that means, then the גזירה שוה gzera shava
of
you know tells the זקני זקני ziknei ziknei tells us that here
too it is the בית דין הגדול. beis din hagadol. אף כאן
מיוחדים שבזקניך. af kan miyuchadim shebiziknecha.
So now so that's why and then I have שופטיך shoftecha three
to tell me two more. So the גמרא gemara says one minute:
אי יליף ליליף כולה מהתם זקניך ושופטיך למה לי? ee yalif leyalif
kula mehasam zekenecha v'shoftecha lama li? If you're making a גזירה שוה
gzera shava to פר העלם דבר של ציבור, par helam davar shel
tzibur, then why don't you learn like everything from there? Meaning because
like we just said on the previous דף, daf, you know, that
this was that we learned out five for from, you know, from
the פר העלם דבר של ציבור par helam davar shel tzibur also,
so why not learn it out so why not learn it out
from there? Why do you learn if you're really making a גזירה
שוה gzera shava you could learn the number as well? So
אי יליף ליליף כולה מהתם זקניך ושופטיך למה לי? ee yalif leyalif
kula mehasam zekenecha v'shoftecha lama li? So אלא ו' דשופטיך למניינא. ella
vav d'shoftecha l'minyana.
So he acts the actual ו, vav, you're right, even רבי יהודה
rebbi yehuda needed שופטיך shoftecha to tell you בית דין הגדול, beis
din hagadol, but the ושופטיך v'shoftecha is to tell you also count
this twice and count this also to tell you two more judges.
רבי שמעון ו' לא דריש rebbi shimon vav lo darish and רבי
שמעון rebbi shimon does not דורש darshen the ו. vav. Okay fine,
so now we figured out the three-five debate. So pretty much identical
to the debate that they had by what is exactly the same
three versus five, and each one deciding which, you know, whether the
פסוקים psukim you're going to learn two plus two plus one gets
you five or two plus one gets you three. The same way
we had the discussion by פר העלם דבר par helam davar we
have the issue by עגלה ערופה. egla arufa. So now the גמרא
gemara continues. Okay, אלא... ella... אלא מעתה *Ella me'ata* ויצאו שנים ומדדו
שנים *v'yatzu shnayim u'madedu shnayim* when it also speaks about them going
and measuring to see which is the city that's closest to the
murdered body, so why don't we every time it speaks in the
plural that should be adding two more participants? So ויצאו *v'yatzu* is
two more, ומדדו *u'madedu*, they measure, הרי תשעה *harei tisha*, so that
should get you up to nine for רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* and
הרי שבעה *harei shiva* for רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* to get you
up to seven. So Gemara says no, הוא מיבעי ליה לכדתניא *hu
mibaya lei l'chidetanya*, we need that to tell you what we taught
in the Beraita: ויצאו *v'yatzu* הן ולא שלוחן *hein v'lo shluchan*. They
have to go out, so it's the same they, not a new
they. One wonders when the Gemara keeps on adding these words, you
know, say we could have added two more, two more, how do
you describe what they're doing without using these verbs? Okay, but anyway,
what would have been the alternative? But anyway, the Gemara is saying
to the degree that you see this word as extra, it's coming
to tell you they themselves have to do it, they can't have
representatives go and do it for them. Okay, ומדדו *u'madedu*, they have
to measure it, שאפילו נמצא בעליל לעיר *she'afilu nimtza be'alil l'ir*, even
if it is very clearly, like through a crystal, like you know,
it's obviously right next to this city, it's two feet away from
this city's borders, nevertheless, top of י"ד עמוד ב' *yud daled amud
bet*, צריך לעסוק במדידה *tzarich la'asok bimdida*, there's still a mitzvah to
do the act of measuring. Okay, מתניתין דלא כי האי תנא Masnisin
d'lo k'hai tanna, *matnitin d'lo ki hai tanna*, now our Mishnah about
three and five is not like the following תנא Tanna, *tanna*, דתניא
*detanya*, taught in a Beraita: רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov אומר *Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov omer*, ויצאו זקניך ושופטיך *v'yatzu zkeinecha
v'shoftecha*, same pasuk we're starting from. זקניך זו סנהדרין Sanhedrin *zkeinecha zu
Sanhedrin*, so זקניך *zkeinecha* tells you that
it is the Sanhedrin, meaning the entire Sanhedrin. We're not doing two
plus two plus whatever, not some small microcosm of it. The whole
Sanhedrin goes out. ושופטיך *v'shoftecha*, and what does it mean your judges,
after you've said the elders? So judges like political authority, or you
know, it's not just the, I mean, think about the שופטים *shoftim*
in, you know, in יהושע *Yehoshua* and שופטים *Shoftim*. Those were the
political leaders. So זה מלך melech וכהן גדול *zeh melech v'kohen gadol*,
a Melech and a Kohen Gadol. Interesting, Kohen Gadol. So everything that
represents religious authority, Torah, Beit Hamikdash, political authority, everybody goes out
for this of, you know, for this case of the עגלה ערופה
egla arufa *egla arufa*. מלך Melech. דכתיב *melech d'chtiv*, מלך במשפט יעמיד
ארץ *melech bemishpat ya'amid aretz*, the king with justice will up, you
know, found the land, will give the foundation of the, for the,
for the land. So that's the idea of the king associated with
justice, שופטיך *shoftecha*. כהן גדול kohen gadol דכתיב *kohen gadol d'chtiv*, ובאת
אל הכהנים הלוים ואל השופט *u'vata el hakohanim haleviyim v'el hashofet*, which
is a little funny because that says the Kohanim Leviyim and the
Shofet, which makes the Shofet different from the Kohanim and Leviyim. Alright,
but somehow for, for him it's really major, you know, that sense
of taking responsibility that somebody was murdered and knowing that you can't
pro, there's a concern you'll never find the murderer and did we
do our responsibility to that, that has to be like the whole
leadership of the country comes out. Okay, now איבעיא להו *iba'ya lehu*,
now they ask the question: רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov בחדא פליגי או בתרתי פליגי *Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov bachada pligi
o bitartei pligi*? Does he argue on one thing or does he
argue on two things? What does that mean? פליגי במלך וכהן גדול
פליגי *pligi bemelech v'kohen gadol pligi*. Does he say what he's really
adding is just adding the king and the Kohen Gadol? אבל בסנהדרי
אי כרבי יהודה אי כרבי שמעון *aval beSanhedrei i k'Rabbi Yehuda i
k'Rabbi Shimon*. But when it comes to the Sanhedrin, he's not saying
the whole Sanhedrin, he'll say whatever Rabbi Yehuda or Rabbi Shimon would
say, three or five, some representation. או דילמא בסנהדרי נמי פליגי *o
dilma beSanhedrei nami pligi*? Or maybe he also says with the Sanhedrin,
I mean the entire Sanhedrin? דאמר כולה סנהדרי בעינן *d'amar kula Sanhedrei
ba'inan*. You need the whole Sanhedrin, which is a little bit what
it sounds like. אמר רב יוסף Rav Yosef. תא שמע Ta shema,
*Amar Rav Yosef ta shma*, come and hear. We have a Beraita
or Mishnah: מצאוהו בבית פגי והמרה עליהם *metza'uhu beBeit Pagi v'himra aleihem*.
יכול תהא המראתו המראה *yachol tehei hamra'ato hamra'ah*? תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*:
וקמת ועלית אל המקום *v'kamta v'alita el hamakom*. מלמד שהמקום גורם *melamed
shehamakom gorem*. Okay, so if the זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre *zaken mamre*
finds the Sanhedrin and they were not in the place where they
sit, you know, in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beit Hamikdash*, okay,
and they're not in the לשכת הגזית Lishkas Hagaziz. *Lishkat Hagazit*, which
was right there, you know, on the הר הבית *Har Habayit*, but
they were in בית פגי *Beit Pagi*, which is some place that
is within ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim* but it's like clearly not on Har
Habayit. Okay, and that's where he is rejecting their authority and doing
his teaching and the type of thing that would get him labeled
as a זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre *zaken mamre*. So perhaps that rebellion
would be considered a rebellion? תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*: וקמת ועלית אל
המקום *v'kamta v'alita el hamakom*. You should go to the place. מלמד
שהמקום גורם *melamed shehamakom gorem*. It is only when that, you know,
person who is not abiding by them is doing his rebellion when
they are sitting in their seat of authority on the Har Habayit.
Okay, only then does he get the status of זקן ממרא zaken
mamre, *zaken mamre*. Now the Gemara says: דנפק מאן *d'nafak man*? How
many people are not sitting in the לשכת הגזית Lishkas Hagaziz? *Lishkat
Hagazit* that he's having this debate with them and, you know, and
being defiant? אילימא מקצתן *ilima miktzatan*,
maybe only some of them are there and some are still back
in the לשכת הגזית Lishkas Hagaziz, *Lishkat Hagazit*. דילמא הנך דאיכא גואי
קיימי כוותיה *dilma hanach d'ika gava'i kaimi kavatei*. So how do you,
how could we even judge that this is a real defiance of
authority? Maybe if you would
actually bring in those who weren't there, they might agree with him
and and you know they might they might turn everybody around. It's
not you know it wouldn't be if if the whole סנהדרין Sanhedrin
isn't convened then he's not how can you judge this as being
defiant of authority?
We don't know what the end conclusion will be. So אילימא כוותיה
Eileima kivasei על פי דנפקא כולה. al pi denafka kula. So it
must be the whole סנהדרין Sanhedrin is not in there you know
is not sitting in the לשכת הגזית. Lishkas Hagaziz, So what are
they doing? They're going on a field trip? Like okay, you know,
they don't have to be there 24/7, they can go home, but
it sounds like the סנהדרין Sanhedrin is all present. So what is
the entire סנהדרין Sanhedrin? doing present outside of the לשכת הגזית? Lishkas
Hagaziz. למה אילימא לדבר רשות, Lama eileima lidvar reshus,
if it's for something that's
you know optional, they don't have an obligation to leave the לשכת
הגזית, Lishkas Hagaziz מי מצו נפקי, mi matzu nafkei, they can't leave?
והכתיב Vihaksiv the פסוק pasuk says שררך אגן הסהר... Sareich agan hasohar...
excuse me, שררך אגן הסהר, Shareireich agan hasohar,
your navel, your belly button is like a round goblet. This is
from שיר השירים. Shir Hashirim. אל יחסר המזג, Al yichsar hamazeg,
the mixed wine will not be lacking. So what does that mean?
Well we learn it out to mean that the that you cannot
be lacking from a certain number that are remain in the לשכת
הגזית, Lishkas Hagaziz you know in the hewn stone. So
take a look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi tells you this, כתיב
ודרשינן בהכא בדיני ממונות אל יחסר המזג אם נצרך אחד מהם לצאת,
ksiv vedarshinan be'hacha bidinei mamonos al yichsar hamazeg im nitzrach echad meihem
latzeis, if one of the סנהדרין Sanhedrin had to leave from the...
אם יש שם כ"ג כנגד סנהדרי קטנה יוצא ואם לאו אינו יוצא.
im yesh sham chaf-gimel kineged sanhedri kitana yotzei ve'im lav eino yotzei.
If there's enough there like the סנהדרי קטנה sanhedri kitana then they
can go, if not they can't go. And some want...
so how does this idea say they can't be lacking and okay
wine is תורה Torah relates somehow to סנהדרין? Sanhedrin But how does
it tell you that you know as long as you leave a
סנהדרי קטנה, sanhedri kitana, how do you learn that you know from
there? So if you look at תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos says אל
יחסר המזג כדאמר שאם הוצרך אחד מהם לצאת אם יש בו כ"ג
יוצא. al yichsar hamazeg kide'amar she'im hutzrach echad meihem latzeis im yesh
bo chaf-gimel yotzei. If there's 23 that are left then they then
a person can go off for a private matter. ואם לאו אינו
יוצא והיינו כמזיגה. ve'im lav eino yotzei vehaynu kemiziga.
This is the idea of mixed wine, why? דעל חד תרי, de'al
chad terei,
because a mixed wine is one part wine, two parts water. Now
the problem is often it's one part wine, three parts water. תוספות
Tosafos discusses it, but just like the mixed wine you need at
least that essence that one third that's still wine, still there, so
you need at least the you know the 23, a בית דין
קטן, beis din katan, a סנהדרין קטנה sanhedrin kitana there. Now תוספות
Tosafos has a cute thing at the end, if you look at
the end of תוספות Tosafos about five lines from the end, ויש
מפרשים אל יחסר המזג שלא יחסר בגימטריא מזג. veyeish mefarshim al yichsar
hamazeg shelo yichsar begematriya mazeg.
Don't be losing מזג. mazeg. So what is that? That's 50 in
גימטריא, gematriya, שזה חמשים. shezeh chamishim. So if you're missing 50, then
you're left with 21. So you can't do that. But so you
have to leave at least 22, you can't be losing 50, you
have to... you can only miss 49. 22... 22 אין בית דין
שקול, ein beis din shakol, 23. Okay. So from this we learn
that you have to leave a that you have to leave a
בית דין, beis din, a minimal בית דין beis din of 23
in the לשכת הגזית. So, but we're also saying that the that
the זקן ממרא could a scenario where he could be debating with
the בית דין beis din and it would have to be the
entire סנהדרין Sanhedrin or else it wouldn't constitute a defiance because maybe
with the others there the the conclusion would have come out differently.
And so and so what are they all doing there together right?
So the גמרא Gemara says so let's read that again. למה אילימא
לדבר רשות, Lama eileima lidvar reshus, if it's they're just going off
for personal matters again it wouldn't explain what they're all doing collected
together. But anyway מי מצו נפקי. mi matzu nafkei. So then they
can't be going out in the middle of the day for some
personal matter, they're all going out to the ball game, okay, because
it says שררך אגן הסהר אל יחסר המזג. Shareireich agan hasohar al
yichsar hamazeg. So they can go home, the day can be over,
okay, but if it's if if the day isn't over then they
can't all be leaving here for a personal matter. אלא פשיטא לדבר
מצוה, Ela pishita lidvar mitzvah, it must be that if they're leaving,
they're all leaving and they're doing it for a דבר מצוה, dvar
mitzvah, not a דבר רשות. dvar reshus. So and what are they
doing? You could just say the fact they're all collected together obviously
means it's some type of a סנהדרין Sanhedrin function. היכי דמי לאו
למדידת עגלה, Heichi dami lav lemedidas egla,
it must be what else would you need the entire בית דין
beis din to leave the לשכת הגזית for were it not to
do this thing of עגלה ערופה egla arufa and maybe that's what
he and the זקן ממרא were debating, whether you know some aspect
of that. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב היא. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov hi.
It must be רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rebbi Elazar ben Yaakov, דאמר
כולי סנהדרין בעינן. de'amar kulei sanhedrin bainan. Okay.
So therefore that would be a proof to show you that רבי
אלעזר בן יעקב Rebbi Elazar ben Yaakov would say that you know
not only you need a כהן Kohen גדול and a מלך but
you also need the entire סנהדרין Sanhedrin because of a scenario where
we know the entire סנהדרין Sanhedrin. could leave the לשכת הגזית on
a דבר מצוה. dvar mitzvah. So, you know, one must imagine that
there could be another legitimate reason and אביי Abaye comes and says
what that is. So אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye
responded, לא כגון שיצאו להוסיף על העיר ועל העזרות. lo kigon sheyatzu
lehosif al ha'ir ve'al ha'azaros. No, they you need the סנהדרין Sanhedrin
and they're coming to do another thing to expand the parameters of
the עזרה, azara, you know in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, what
exactly are those boundaries or of ירושלים. Yerushalayim and in order to
expand those boundary lines and parameters and give קדושה, kedusha, you need
the entire סנהדרין. כדתנן, kidtnan, אין מוסיפין על העיר ועל העזרות, ein
mosifin al hair ve'al ha'azarot, you can't add to the city of
ירושלים Yerushalayim. or to the עזרות, azaros, the different courtyards of the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash אלא בבית דין של שבעים ואחד. ela b'veis
din shel shivim v'echad. Okay, so we don't know what רבי אלעזר
בן עזריה Rebbi Elazar ben Azaryah would say, except we have another
ברייתא. braisa. רבי
אלעזר בן יעקב, excuse me. תניא כוותיה דרב יוסף, tanya k'vasei d'Rav
Yosef, but we found a ברייתא braisa like רב יוסף. מצאו בבית
פאגי והמרא
עליהן, matza'u b'Beis Pagi v'himra aleihen, again talking about the זקן ממרא,
he found them outside of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash? and he
rebelled against them. Now, and then this ברייתא braisa though spells out,
what are they doing outside of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash, כגון
שיצאו למדידת עגלה ולהוסיף על העיר ועל העזרות, k'gon sheyatzu l'midas egla
va'lahosif al hair v'al ha'azaros,
like they all left in order to do the measuring of the
עגלה ערופה egla arufa, or to expand the boundaries of the city.
So that spells out those two scenarios. יכול תהא המראה המראה, תלמוד
לומר וקמת ועלית אל המקום אשר יבחר ה' אלוקיך מלמד שהמקום גורם.
yachol tihe hamrasa hamrasa, talmud lomar v'kamta v'alita el hamakom asher yivchar
Hashem Elokecha, melamed shehamakom gorem.
Now, it'll have to be in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash but
this ברייתא braisa spells out that they actually could be leaving for
the מדידה medida of the עגלה ערופה, so there's the position of
רבי אלעזר בן יעקב that three or five is not sufficient, you
need the entire סנהדרין plus כהן Kohen plus מלך. Okay, now we
continue. נטע רבעי ומעשר שני שאין דמיו ידועין בשלשה. neta revai maaser
sheni she'ein damav yedu'in b'shlosha. So now we're going onto something completely
different, you know, the redeeming of נטע רבעי neta revai מעשר שני,
maaser sheni, נטע רבעי neta revai fourth year after a tree was
three years of ערלה orlah or מעשר שני, maaser sheni, two out
of if you know years one and two and four and five
of the שמיטה shmita cycle, you would take מעשר שני maaser sheni
after the first מעשר maaser would go to the לוי, Levi, you'd
take מעשר שני maaser sheni and bring it to ירושלים. Yerushalayim, If
you didn't want to bring it to ירושלים, Yerushalayim a lot of
fruit to shlep there, you would redeem it on money, transfer to
money, and you'd bring the money to ירושלים and you would use
the money. Now we did skip over in the משנה החליצה והמיאונין
בשלשה, mishna hachalitza v'hami'unim b'shlosha, but that gets discussed in יבמות, Yevamos,
so the גמרא's Gemara not discussing it here. Okay, so now let's
take a look at what this idea is that you need three.
Here I am, you know, I'm just in my private home and
I'm dealing with all of my apples or whatever it is and
I want to transfer to money. I gotta call a בית דין
Beis Din in order to transfer to money? Like what's going on
here? So let's take a look.
תנו רבנן איזהו מעשר שני שאין דמיו ידועין? tanu rabbanan: eizo hu
maaser sheni she'ein damav yedu'in? So it means, so oh, so I
missed that important phrase, right? If it's like, oh look, we all
know what the price of apples is, you know so much a
bushel, there's a standard market rate, market price, you don't need to
involve anybody else. But if it's a case where there's some reason
that it's uncertain what price to affix to it, then we're afraid
that you might not be totally objective and you need to bring
in other people. So what is that scenario?
כגון שאין דמיו ידועין, פירות שהרקיבו. k'gon she'ein damav yedu'in, peiros she'hirkivu.
If the fruits have rotted, so you know you could still sell
them for animal food, a little bit rotted, they're grade B apples,
not grade A apples. ויין שהקרים v'yayin she'hikrim or the wine that
developed like a film. So once it's substandard and you know the
market exact value for that is less certain. ומעות שהחלידו u'maos she'hechlidu
or if it's money, you know, and I guess transferring money to
money or whatever, you know, that is or maybe it means the
money you're transferring it on is, because money to money is a
whole question, anyway, you know, has gotten rusted. So in those cases
there's a judgment call and we're afraid that you will not be
totally objective. So okay, so now you need a בית דין Beis
Din and is it a בית דין Beis Din of סמוכים? smuchim?
So let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. תנו רבנן,
tanu rabbanan, our Rabbis
taught: מעשר שני שאין דמיו ידועין פודנו אותו בשלשה לקוחות. maaser sheni
she'ein damav yedu'in, podno oto b'shlosha lakuchos. You
redeem it with three buyers. Okay,
now that's going to be very clear, we're not talking about a
בית דין. Beis Din. Okay, you get three people here that know,
you know, if you look at רש"י Rashi לקוחות: lakuchos:
סוחרים בקיאין בשומא. socharim b'ki'in b'shuma. You get like people that are
in the business who are good at assessing it. You get an
objective independent assessment. Quite bizarre because the whole idea here is about
the authority of בית דין Beis Din and all of a sudden
this idea of three has nothing to do with בית דין, Beis
Din, right? You just get three people to be assessors because you
need an objective assessment. How do I know it has nothing to
do with בית דין? Beis Din? Let's look at the next line.
אבל לא בשלשה שאינן לקוחות, aval lo b'shlosha she'einan lakuchos, but you
can't do three that are not buyers, are not people that are
like experts in the field. ואפילו נכרי אחד מהן, v'afillu nochri echad
mehen,
and you know what, even a non-Jew can be one of the
three. Alright, so clearly it's not a בית דין. Beis Din. Bizarre
that it's included in the משנה. mishna. ואפילו אחד מהם בעל הבית,
v'afillu echad mehem ba'al habayis,
now even one of them can be the owner himself. You need
to bring in two others because you don't trust him to be
totally objective but you know he presumably if he grows apples he
also knows the business and he can have his input as well.
בעי רבי ירמיה:
שלשה ומטילין לתוך כיס אחד מהו. ba'ei Rebbi Yirmiyah: shlosha u'matilin l'toch
kis echad ma hu. Let's say it's three different people. people but
they all are like in business together. So does that count as
like three separate assessments? All right, so what's the story?
תא שמע, come and hear. איש ושתי נשיו פודים מעשר שני, Ish
ushtey nashav podin maaser sheni, so you see that a man and
his two wives can do it. So there you have it, three
people that are all effectively one household and in business together. Okay,
so this would be a way around it also because it could
be the owner, the owner comes and he gets his wife and
maybe his older son, you know, whatever it would
be, and together they assess it. All right, look, if you want
to cheat, you want to cheat, hopefully people want to do the
right thing but they're just trying to be objective. So the גמרא
Gemara says that's not a total proof that they are all the
same household in the sense or in business together. דילמא כגון רב
פפא ובת אבא סורא, Dilma kegon Rav Papa uvas Abba Sura, maybe
it's like רב פפא Rav Papa and the daughter of אבא סורא.
Abba Sura. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, אשת רב פפא, Eishes
Rav Papa, כדאמרינן בכתובות, kid'amrinan Bi'Kesuvos, אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa,
אמרה לי בת אבא סורא, Amra li bas Abba Sura, והוות עבדה
לנפשה. vehavas avda lenafsha. And you know, she was, you know, she
earned her own money, she didn't live off of רב הונא. Rav
Huna. Okay, so in that type of a case, of רב פפא,
Rav Papa, excuse me, you know, she would be considered an independent
authority and so you can't prove if they really are all three
essentially in the same business, living off of the same income and
so on, whether that would work or would not work. Now by
the way, תוספות Tosfos says when some say that the idea of
שלשה לקוחות shlosha lakuchos that you would do an auction and you
would go by the highest bid of the auction, but he says
this whole discussion about the wives and מטילין לתוך כיס אחד matilin
letoch kis echad does not imply that that's the case. All right,
let's take a look at one more piece. ההקדש בשלשה, Hahekdesh bishlosha,
if you sanctify something and then you want to redeem it onto,
again, case of redemption, so here, and this is different because the
case of מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and נטע רבעי Neta Revai was
your property, הקדש Hekdesh you're transferring it, it belongs to הקדש Hekdesh
and now there's nobody representing the בית המקדש and you're transferring it
out of the right of הקדש, Hekdesh, you know, you sanctified your
car and now you are going to transfer it to money and
you're going to assess the value of that car. So מתניתין דלא
כי האי תנא, our משנה Mishna is not like the following תנא,
דתניא רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Detanya Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, again with
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, אומר אפילו צינורא של
הקדש צריכה עשרה בני אדם לפדותה. Omer afilu tzinora shel hekdesh tzricha
asara bnei adam lifdosa. Even if it was like a fork of
הקדש, Hekdesh, a tiny little thing, you need ten people, three is
not enough. אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי, Amar leh Rav Papa le-Abaye,
so רב פפא Rav Papa said to אביי, Abaye, בשלמא לרבי אליעזר
בן יעקב דאמר כשמואל, Bishlama le-Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov d'amar k'Shmuel, I
get where he gets ten. He's saying like שמואל, Shmuel, דאמר שמואל
עשרה כהנים כתובין בפרשה, d'amar Shmuel asara kohanim kesuvin b'parsha, it says
כהן Kohen ten times in the פרשה. parsha. What פרשה? parsha? At
the end of
מסעי... Massei...
excuse me, I meant בחקתי, Bechukosai, end of במדבר, Bamidbar, end of
ויקרא, Vayikra, okay, at the end of
בחקתי, Bechukosai, it talks about if a person sanctifies his house. And
there it says, I'll just read the פסוק, pasuk, it says like
this, ואם כל בהמה אשר יקריבו ממנה קרבן לה', Veim kol behema
asher yakrivu mimena korban l'Hashem, this is in פרק כ"ז פסוק י"א,
perek chaf-zayin pasuk yud-aleph, והעמיד את הבהמה לפני הכהן, vehe'emid es habehema
lifnei hakohen, והעריך הכהן אתה בין טוב ובין רע כערכך הכהן כן
יהיה. ve'erich hakohen osa bein tov uvein ra k'erkecha hakohen ken yihye.
It has a whole process of assessing the value of something that
is not הקדש Hekdesh as a קרבן, korban, but הקדש Hekdesh to
be owned by בדק הבית Bedek Habayis and that the כהן Kohen
is involved and he assesses the value. And then it deals with
the case of
sanctifying land, and
so in that פרשה parsha right there by the בהמה, behema, it
says the word כהן Kohen three times. Now that comes right after
the פרשה parsha of ערכין. erchin. Now ערכין erchin when you say
this person's ערך erech is on me, there's a fixed chart based
on male, female, and age, how much that is, but at the
very last פסוק pasuk of the section of ערכין erchin right before
it gets to the case that we were reading, it says ואם
מך הוא מערכך, ve'im mach hu me-erkecha, if the person can't afford
the ערך, erech, והעמידו לפני הכהן, vehe'emido lifnei hakohen, והעריך אתו הכהן,
ve'erich oso hakohen, על פי אשר תשיג יד הנודר יעריכנו הכהן. al
pi asher tasig yad hanoder ya'aricenu hakohen. The כהן Kohen can readjust
the ערך erech if the person is poor. Now it says the
word כהן Kohen in that one פסוק pasuk three times. So it
says three times the word כהן Kohen by ערכין, erchin, three times
by redeeming by the case of הקדש, Hekdesh, and then four times
afterwards it talks about sanctifying land, okay, so if you put them
all together, three, three, and four, you get ten. So the גמרא
Gemara says I get the position of ten,
so like שמואל, Shmuel, דאמר שמואל עשרה כהנים כתובין בפרשה, d'amar Shmuel
asara kohanim kesuvin b'parsha, it says כהן Kohen, ten times. Now you
don't need כהנים kohanim ten times, we'll see you need ten people,
only one of them has to be a כהן, Kohen we'll get
to that tomorrow. But at least you get the idea of ten,
because if you look at the entire
פרשה, parsha, you add them all up, that's what you get. אלא
רבנן שלשה מנא להו? Ela rabanan shlosha mna lehu? But where do
the רבנן Rabbis get three? And the answer is pretty obvious because
it says three in the פרשה parsha by הקדש, Hekdesh, right? It
says three by ערכין, erchin, three by הקדש, Hekdesh, four by קרקע.
karka. So that's what the גמרא Gemara suggests, וכי תימא דכתיבי בהו
שלשה שלשה, vechi teima dechsivi behu shlosha shlosha, it says it three
times, קרקעות דכתיבי בהו ארבעה תסגי בארבעה. karka'os dechsivi behu arba'ah tisgei
be'arba'ah. Fine, when you get to the land, it only says כהן
kohen four times, so four should be enough. But we know that
everybody agrees that when it comes by land, you need ten.
וכי תימא הכי נמי vechi teima hachi nami אלא מאי דמשנינן. ella
mai de-mshaninan. How do
you, how do you come to the number ten by the land?
Because you don't say it just says four times כהן kohen by
the land. You add up everything that, every time it says כהן
prior to that and you get a total of ten. So if
you go back to the previous section where it's dealing with בהמה
טמאה, behema tme'a, so, okay, maybe you don't add up everything, but
you should certainly add up until that point. So the גמרא Gemara
says, הקדש דאשתלמו בו שיתא hekdesh de-ishtalmu bo shita לבעי שיתא. libei
shita. So by הקדש, hekdesh, at least it says six up to
that point. So you should require six. If you're going require ten
by קרקע, karka, you should require six by הקדש. hekdesh. And the
גמרא Gemara ends with קשיא. kashya. That's a good question. We don't
know the answer. Alright, we'll end here now.